<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC4271 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6811 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6811.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7454 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7454.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7908 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7908.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8092 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8092.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8205 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8205.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-open-policy SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-open-policy.xml">
<!--
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-idr-aspath-orf SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-aspath-orf.xml">

<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-idr-route-leak-detection-mitigation SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-route-leak-detection-mitigation.xml">

<!ENTITY I-D.draft-sriram-idr-route-leak-solution-discussion SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-sriram-idr-route-leak-solution-discussion.xml">
-->
]>


<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-idr-route-leak-detection-mitigation-11" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Route Leak Detection and Mitigation"> Methods for Detection and Mitigation of BGP Route Leaks </title>

    <author fullname="Kotikalapudi Sriram" initials="K." role="editor" surname="Sriram">
      <organization abbrev="USA NIST">USA National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
      <address>
         <postal>
          <street>100 Bureau Drive</street>
          <city>Gaithersburg</city>
          <region>MD</region>
          <code>20899</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ksriram@nist.gov</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Alexander Azimov" initials="A." role="editor" surname="Azimov">
      <organization abbrev="Yandex">Yandex</organization>
      <address>
         <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Moscow</city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>Russia</country>
        </postal>
        <email>a.e.azimov@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2019" />

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>IDR and SIDR</workgroup>

    <keyword>BGP, Route Leak Detection, Route-Leak Mitigation, BGP Security</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        Problem definition for route leaks and enumeration of types of route leaks are provided in RFC 7908.
        This document describes a inter-AS (multi-hop) solution for detection and mitigation route leaks which is based on conveying route-leak detection information in two new well-known BGP communities: route leak detection community (RLD) and route leak notification community (RLN).
        These communities gives ISPs an easy way to detect route leaks, and, if needed, propagate information about such incidents.
        This solution complements the intra-AS (local AS) route-leak avoidance solution that is described in ietf-idr-bgp-open-policy draft.
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        RFC 7908 <xref target="RFC7908"></xref> provides a definition of the route leak problem, and enumerates several types of route leaks.
        For this document, the definition that is applied is that a route leak occurs when a route received from a transit provider or a lateral peer is forwarded (against commonly used policy) to another transit provider or a lateral peer.
        The commonly used policy is that a route received from a transit provider or a lateral peer may be forwarded only to customers.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document describes a solution for detection and mitigation route leaks which is based on conveying route-leak information in a Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) community.
        These document specified two well-known communities for these purpose - route leak detection (RLP) and route leak notification (RLN) community.
        Its configuration policies MUST be defined according to peering relations between ISPs.
        If BGP Roles described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-open-policy"></xref> are configured community configuration should implemented in code of routing software.
      </t>
      <t>
        Described technique can be incrementally deployed.
        If a group of big ISPs or/and IXes deploy proposed route marking, then they would be helping each other by blocking route leaks that can happen between them.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="relations" title="Peering Relationships">
      <t>
        As described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-open-policy"></xref> there are several common peering relations foe eBGP sessions:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Provider - sender is a transit provider to neighbor;</t>
          <t>Customer - sender is customer of neighbor;</t>
          <t>RS - sender is route server at internet exchange point (IX)</t>
          <t>RS-client - sender is client of RS at internet exchange point (IX)</t>
          <t>Peer - sender and neighbor are peers;</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        If the route is announced to a customer or RS-client it MUST go 'only down' and should not be received by other ISPs from links with customers, peers or at IX route servers from RS-clients.
        The described below community provide an easy way to maintain this rule.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="semantics" title="Route-Leak Detection Community">
      <t>
The key principle is that, in the event of a route leak, a receiving router in a transit-provider AS (e.g., referring to <xref target="fig1"></xref>, ISP2 (AS2) router) should be able to detect from the RLP community in the update message that its customer AS (e.g., AS3 in <xref target="fig1"></xref>) should not have forwarded the update (towards the transit-provider AS). Likewise when the update is received from a lateral peer. This means that at least one of the ASes in the AS path of the update put RLP information in RLP community to indicate that it sent the update to its customer or lateral peer, but forbade any subsequent 'Up' (customer to provider) or 'Lateral' (peer to peer) forwarding.
      </t>

<figure align="center" anchor="fig1" title="Illustration of the basic notion of a route leak.">
  <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
 
                                   /\              /\
                                    \ route-leak(P)/
                                     \ propagated / 
                                      \          /  
           +------------+    peer    +------------+
     ______| ISP1 (AS1) |----------->|  ISP2 (AS2)|---------->
    /       ------------+  prefix(P) +------------+ route-leak(P)
   | prefix |          \   update      /\        \  propagated
    \  (P)  /           \              /          \
     -------   prefix(P) \            /            \   
                  update  \          /              \          
                           \        /route-leak(P)  \/
                           \/      /
                        +---------------+
                        | customer(AS3) |
                        +---------------+

]]></artwork>
 </figure>

<t>
The RLP information contained in the RLP community consists of one or two AS numbers (ASNs) and has the following semantics:
</t>
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>
Down Only (DO) indication: ASN of the most recent RLP-aware AS in the path to assert that it sent the update to a customer or lateral peer;
</t>
<t>
Leak detected (L) indication: ASN of the first RLP-aware AS in the path to assert that it forwarded the route from a customer or lateral peer despite detecting a leak (to avoid unreachability).
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
If the RLP community is present in an update, it will always contain a single DO. However, L need not be always present. (Note: The bits designated to carry L may be always present along with a DO, except that a default value (all zeros) is carried in L when no AS in the current AS path needed to assert L.) Once an AS asserts L (Leak detected) by inserting its ASN value, it MUST not be changed subsequently as the update propagates. But the ASN value in DO (Down Only) is changeable along the AS path per its definition above.
</t>
<t>
Design assumption 1: Operators desire to avoid unreachability. So, a design assumption here is that in the absence of an alternative route, an AS may select and forward a route that is detected to be a leak. (Note: This is the reason Leak detected (L) indication is part of the design.)
</t>
<t>
Design assumption 2: An AS that is RLP-aware (i.e., implements the RLP solution in this document) MUST also implement an intra-AS solution for route leak avoidance in the local AS. The latter solution uses an intra-AS signaling mechanism (see <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-open-policy"></xref>, Section 3.7 of <xref target="RLP-Discussion"></xref>). By doing this, the AS locally prevents the leaking of routes learned from a transit provider or lateral peer to another transit provider or lateral peer. Why this is critical to the overall solution is made clear in slides 7 and 8 of <xref target="sriram2"></xref>.
</t>
<section anchor="format" title="Format of the RLP Community">

<t>
The format of the RLP community using a single Large Community is shown in <xref target="fig2"></xref>.
</t>
<figure align="center" anchor="fig2" title="Format of the RLP Community using a Large Community [RFC8092].">
  <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       Global Administrator  (IANA assigned for RLP)           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Local Data Part 1 = DO (ASN value)                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Local Data Part 2 = L (ASN value)                  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
 </figure>



</section>
</section>
<section anchor="receiver" title="Route Leak Detection Rules and the Ingress Router (Receiver) Actions">

<t>
A received BGP update is determined to be a route leak if:
</t>
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>
if L is present in the update;
</t>
<t>
else (L is absent), the update is received from a customer and DO is present;
</t>
<t>
else (L is absent), the update is received from a lateral peer and DO is present that is not the lateral peer's ASN.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Note: Here by "L is present" we mean that its value is not the default value (all zeros) but is a proper ASN. Effectively "L is absent" if its value is the default value.
</t>
<t>
In steps 2 and 3 above, the ingress router (receiver) MUST add L = local ANS. Doing this prior to the best path selection process is necessary. Also, if the route is selected as best path, then L is already set correctly before the egress router (sender) acts on it.
</t>

</section>
<section anchor="decision" title="Route Selection Policy">
<t>
Minimum Default Policy: Whenever there is a choice between a customer route and a provider route that are both detected to be leaks (L is present), then lower the LocalPref to X (TBD by operator) for each of them. Then shortest path criterion would typically make the customer route preferred. (Note: This would help mitigate any possibility of persistent oscillation; see slide #7 in <xref target="sriram1"></xref>.)
</t>
<t>
Generalized Minimum Default Policy: Whenever there is a choice between multiple routes (customer/peer/provider) and each is detected to be a leak (L is present), then lower the LocalPref to X TBD by operator) for each of them. Then apply shortest path criterion. (Note: Some network operators may find this inadequate; see scenarios #3 and #6 in slides #14 and #16, respectively, in <xref target="sriram2"></xref>. But they may locally modify their policy while respecting the basic principle.)
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sender" title="Egress Router (Sender) Actions">
<t>
After best path selection has been performed, a sender MUST perform the following RLP-related actions on the update to be propagated:
</t>
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>
When propagating a route originated by the local AS to a customer or lateral peer, add DO = local ASN;
</t>
<t>
Else, when propagating a route that already includes a DO (i.e., was received with a DO) to a customer or lateral peer, replace the DO value with the local ASN.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="pseudo" title="Pseudo Code">

<t>
[Begin: receiver action for route leak detection]
</t>
<t>
{Comment: This precedes route selection policy.}
</t>
<t>
<list style="">
<t>
if received route includes L, then save the route in RIB-in as is;
</t>
<t>
else (L is absent), if route is received from a customer and DO is preset, then add L = local ASN;
</t>
<t>
else (L is absent), if route is received from a lateral peer and DO is present that is not the lateral peer's ASN, then add L = local ASN
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
{Comment: "Route does not include L" or "L is absent" only if L is either literally absent or has the default (all zeros) value.}
</t>
<t>
[End: receiver action for route leak detection]
</t>
<t>
----------------------------------------------------------
</t>
<t>
[Begin: route selection policy]
</t>
<t>
<list style="">
<t>
for each route that includes L, lower the LocalPref to X (TBD);
apply best path selection policy*
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
{*Comment: E.g., best path selection based on LocalPref first and then shortest path.}
</t>
<t>
[End: route selection policy]
</t>
<t>
----------------------------------------------------------
</t>
<t>
[Begin: sender action]
</t>
<t>
{Comment: RLP (includes DO and L or just DO) is a *transitive* BGP community and should propagate globally.}
</t>
<t>
<list style="">
<t>
when propagating a route originated by local AS to a customer or lateral peer, add DO = local ASN;
</t>
<t>
when propagating a route that includes a DO (i.e., was received with a DO) to a customer or lateral peer, replace the DO value with the local ASN;
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
[End: sender action]
</t>
</section>

   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
With the use of BGP community, there is often a concern that the community propagates beyond its intended perimeter and causes harm <xref target="streibelt"></xref>. However, that concern does not apply to the RLP community because it is a transitive community that must propagate as far as the update goes.
</t>
<t>
The proposed Route-Leak Protection (RLP) information carried in the RLP community can benefit from cryptographic protection to prevent abuse by malicious actors in the AS path. In the future, if there is BGPsec deployment, the RLP information can be encoded in the Flags field in the Secure_Path Segment in BGPsec updates <xref target="RFC8205"></xref>. So, the cryptographic security mechanisms in BGPsec can also secure the RLP information. The reader is directed to the security considerations provided in <xref target="RFC8205"></xref>.
    </t>

    </section>


    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
IANA is requested to register RLP in the well-known Large Community <xref target="RFC8092"></xref> registry (need help to clarify this). IANA is requested to allocate a new Global Administrator ID for the RLP community (Large Community) (see <xref target="fig2"></xref> in this document). Note that BGP Path Attribute value for Large Community is 32 (IANA allocated) <xref target="RFC8092"></xref>.
</t>

    </section>



    </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>

 <references title="Normative References">
&RFC4271;
 </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
&RFC6811;
&RFC7454;
&RFC7908;
&RFC8092;
&RFC8205;


&I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-open-policy;
      <reference anchor="Luckie" target="http://www.caida.org/~amogh/papers/asrank-IMC13.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>AS Relationships, Customer Cones, and Validation</title>

<author initials="M." surname="Luckie">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
<author initials="B." surname="Huffaker">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
<author initials="A." surname="Dhamdhere">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
<author initials="V." surname="Giotsas">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
<author initials="kc" surname="claffy">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month='October' year='2013' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='' value='IMC 2013' />
      </reference>

<reference anchor="draft-dickson-sidr-route-leak-solns" target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-dickson-sidr-route-leak-solns-01">
        <front>
          <title>Route Leaks -- Proposed Solutions</title>

<author initials="B." surname="Dickson">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month='March' year='2012' />
        </front>
<seriesInfo name='' value='IETF Internet Draft (expired)' />
      </reference>

<!-- draft-sriram-idr-route-leak-solution-discussion-00 (I-D Exists) -->
<reference anchor="RLP-Discussion" target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-sriram-idr-route-leak-solution-discussion-00">
<front>
<title>Design Discussion of Route Leaks Solution Methods </title>
<author initials='K' surname='Sriram (Ed.)' fullname='Kotikalapudi Sriram'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='July' year='2018' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-sriram-idr-route-leak-solution-discussion-00'/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="streibelt" target="https://archive.psg.com//181101.imc-communities.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>BGP Communities: Even more Worms in the Routing Can</title>

<author initials="F." surname="Streibelt et al.">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month='October' year='2018' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='' value='ACM IMC' />
      </reference>


<reference anchor="sriram1" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/meeting/102/materials/slides-102-idr-sessb-route-leaks-merged-solution-00">
        <front>
          <title>Route Leaks Solution Merger of RLP and eOTC Drafts</title>

<author initials="K." surname="Sriram et al.">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month='July' year='2018' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='' value='Presented at the IDR Working Group Meeting, IETF-102, Montreal' />
      </reference>


<reference anchor="sriram2" target="https://www.nist.gov/sites/default/files/documents/2018/10/22/rlp_using_bgp_community-v4.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Solution for Route Leaks Using BGP Communities
</title>

<author initials="K." surname="Sriram et al.">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month='October' year='2018' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='' value='Authors Team Discussion Slides' />
      </reference>



</references>


<section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">

      <t>
The authors wish to thank John Scudder and Susan Hares for their review and comments.
</t>

    </section>

<section title="Contributors" numbered="no">

<t>
The following people made significant contributions to this document and
should be considered co-authors:
</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[

Brian Dickson
Independent
Email: brian.peter.dickson@gmail.com

Doug Montgomery
USA National Institute of Standards and Technology
Email: dougm@nist.gov

Keyur Patel
Arrcus
Email: keyur@arrcus.com

Andrei Robachevsky
Internet Society
Email: robachevsky@isoc.org

Eugene Bogomazov
Qrator Labs
Email: eb@qrator.net

Randy Bush
Internet Initiative Japan
Email: randy@psg.com

]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

</back>

</rfc>

